本期视频由CuriosityStream赞助
This episode of Primal Space is supported by CuriosityStream.
欢迎前往curiositystream.com/primalspace观看上千部纪录片
Watch thousands of documentaries for free by visiting curiositystream.com/primalspace
1990年4月24日 发现号航天飞机将哈勃太空望远镜送入轨道
On the 24th of April, 1990, Space Shuttle Discovery launched the Hubble telescope into orbit.
那是最让人兴奋的一段日子 因为哈勃可以为大家带来震撼的照片
This was an exciting time for space exploration, as Hubble promised to produce mind boggling images,
让我们一睹宇宙早期刚形成的时候的样子
showing us an early view of our universe as it was forming.
但当哈勃一上线 科学家们就发现了其镜面的严重问题
But as soon as Hubble came online, scientists noticed a serious problem with its mirror.
尽管这是当时制造过的最精细的镜面
Although this was the most precisely cut mirror ever made,
但2000纳米的轻微误差却让哈勃没法拍摄清晰的照片
a slight defect of just 2,000 nanometers meant that Hubble failed to produce sharp images.
三年后 科学家们成功镜面进行改造
After 3 years, scientists managed to produce a fix for the mirror
哈勃正式开始揭开宇宙的秘密
and Hubble began scanning the universe for its secrets.
哈勃至今已经运行了近30年
Since then, Hubble has operated for nearly 30 years,
拍摄了无数遥远的恒星与星系的最震撼的照片
capturing the most stunning images of distant stars and galaxies.
但哈勃和万物一样 都有自己的限制
But like everything, Hubble has its limits,
且这架世界上最有名的望远镜 也终将在不久的将来走到生命的尽头
and the world's most famous telescope will eventually come to an end in the not-too-distant future.
可这个“不久”是多久？
But how long does it have left?
哈勃又为何会在观测方面达到自身的极限呢？
And why has it reached a limit in terms of what it can observe?
在哈勃的一生中 它拍摄了数百万张惊人的照片
Throughout its lifetime, Hubble has taken millions of amazing pictures.
它能观测到普通望远镜看不到的 电磁波频谱中其他的部分
It's able to observe other parts of the electromagnetic spectrum that an ordinary telescope couldn't see.
因其位于地球大气之外 所以它拥有观测宇宙的完全无阻挡的视角
Since it's outside of Earth's atmosphere, it has an unobstructed view of the universe
使其相比于地面的望远镜 能观测到更暗更远的物体
which allows it to capture objects that are dimmer and much more distant
than a ground-based telescope ever could.
尽管如此 哈勃拍到的最好的照片大家也看过无数张
Despite this, Hubble's best images have come and gone,
但物理上的限制则让它无法再看到更暗 更远的物体了
and the limitations of physics will likely stop it from seeing anything dimmer or further than it already has.
为了看到宇宙最暗 最远的物体
In order to observe the furthest and dimmest objects in the universe,
你需要有极高的分辨率并能捕捉到尽可能多的光
you need a telescope with an extremely high resolution and the ability to capture as much light as possible.
望远镜的分辨率受制于镜面观测的光的波长
The resolution of a telescope is limited to the number of wavelengths it can fit across its mirror.
望远镜的角分辨率是望远镜分辨两个物体的最小角距离
The angular resolution of a telescope measures its ability to identify two separate objects
that have a short angular distance when observed by a telescope.
计算方法是1.22乘光的波长除以镜面直径
This is given by 1.22 multiplied by the wavelength of the light over the diameter of the mirror.
当观察波长约500纳米可见光时 哈勃的角分辨率约0.05角秒
When observing visible light of about 500nm, Hubble has an angular resolution of about 0.05 arcseconds.
这是人眼分辨能力的一千倍
This beats the human eye's resolution by a factor of 1000.
对于紫外线这种更短波长的电磁波 分辨率则会更好
For even shorter wavelengths like ultraviolet, the resolution gets even better
哈勃的分辨率能达到0.01角秒
and Hubble can achieve an angular resolution as low as 0.01 arcseconds.
哈勃也会受制于自审能观测到的波长类型
Hubble is also limited by the types of wavelengths it can observe.
恒星会发出很大范围波长的光 虽然哈勃也能观察很大范围波长的光
Stars emit a wide range of light, and although Hubble can observe a wide range of wavelengths,
但它却无法观测超过近红外以外的波段
it can't observe anything greater than near infrared.
这限制了它观测远处物体的能力
This limits its ability to look back in time to distant objects.
随着宇宙的膨胀 太空的结构也在随之扩张
As the universe expands, the fabric of space expands with it.
当光在宇宙中传播时 波长会因宇宙的膨胀而拉伸
When light travels through the universe, its wavelength is stretched with the expansion of space.
这意味着当光到达哈勃时
This means that by the time the light arrives at Hubble,
光的波长比它离开光源时更长
the wavelength of the light is longer than when it left the object.
这被称为“红移”
This is known as red shifting.
当物体距离越来越远 光飞行的时间也越长
As the distance to an object increases the longer its light will spend travelling through space
红移的现象也会越明显
and the more red-shifted it will get.
如果光红移太多
If the light is redshifted too much,
它的波长就会跑到哈勃可观测的波长范围外
it could be stretched to a wavelength outside of Hubble's viewing range.
哈勃的主要目标之一就是在已知宇宙范围内探索最遥远的星系
One of the main goals of the Hubble telescope was to find the most distant Galaxy in the known universe.
它在2016年做到了 它发现了星系编号GN-Z11
It achieved this in 2016, when it discovered Galaxy GN-Z11.
该星系位于320亿光年外
This galaxy is located 32 billion light-years away
我们看到的光是它在134亿年前发出的
and the light we see from it shows the Galaxy as it was 13.4 billion years ago.
这个星系已经接近当时哈勃可观测的距离极限了
This Galaxy is at the very limit of how far into the past Hubble can see,
而且这个发现出自某些惊人的巧合
and it was discovered due to some incredible circumstances.
因为这个星系和哈勃之间中性气体刚好非常少
The Galaxy just so happens to be in an area of the universe
where there is very little neutral gas between it and Hubble.
这给了望远镜一个非常好的观测这个星系的视野
This gave the telescope a clear view to observe the Galaxy.
从那个星系发出的光经过另一个星系引发了引力透镜效应
The light coming from the Galaxy passed by another nearby Galaxy which caused it to be gravitationally lensed.
这通常在光因重力被另一个物体拉伸后发生
This happens when the light from an object is bent by the gravitational pull of another object.
本来会错过观测者的光被弯曲后射向了观测者
Light that would otherwise miss the observer is bent in a away which directs it towards the observer.
这让GN-Z11星系的光被放大 刚好能够被哈勃发现
This caused the light from Galaxy GN-Z11 to be magnified, just enough for Hubble to observe it.
直到目前 哈勃已经拍摄这些惊人的照片长达29年
So far, Hubble has been capturing these stunning images for 29 years.
因其设计 哈勃得以在轨运行
Due to it's design, Hubble was capable of being serviced in orbit.
过去若干年 航天飞机载着宇航员五次造访哈勃
Over the years, the Space Shuttle crew visited Hubble on 5 separate missions
去进行维修和失效零件替换
to fix and replace faulty components.
然而 2011年航天飞机退役后 我们就无法那样维护哈勃了
However, since the Shuttle program ended in 2011, we no longer have the ability to maintain Hubble,
望远镜上的零件就开始慢慢损耗了
which is starting to take its toll on the telescope.
哈勃有六个陀螺仪 用于机动与精确指向目标物体
Hubble has 6 gyros onboard which it uses to maneuver and point its telescope precisely towards its target.
在过去五年中坏了三个
In the last 5 years, 3 of these gyros have failed.
即使未来十年哈勃继续正常运行 它的轨道也会慢慢降低
Even if Hubble continues to function over the next decade, its orbit is constantly decaying
在30年代 哈勃将重返大气 在落地前烧毁
and in the 2030's Hubble will crash into the atmosphere and burn up before reaching the ground.
在此事发生之前 下一代太空望远镜将早已进入太空
By the time this happens, the next generation of space telescopes will be in orbit,
拍摄宇宙更加令人震撼的照片
producing even more stunning images of our universe.
但我们永远不会忘记哈勃曾经带给我们的震撼
But Hubble's groundbreaking images will never be forgotten.
虽然哈勃在退役时已经运转了几十年
So although Hubble will be decades old before it retires,
对于它观测到的物体来说 只不过是转瞬间罢了
it's existence will be a mere flash compared to the age of the objects it managed to capture.
不过 望远镜背后伟大的工程学与科学
Nevertheless, the incredible engineering and science behind this telescope
让我们在对宇宙的理解上前进了一大步
helped us take an enormous step forward in our understanding of the universe.
如果你喜欢观看更多有关哈勃的内容 欢迎观看CuriosityStream上的纪录片
If you'd like to watch more about Hubble, check out this documentary on CuriosityStream
其中讲了如何把哈勃的数据转换成如此震撼的照片
which looks at the process of turning Hubble's data into stunning images like this.
CuriosityStream是一家专注于纪录片的视频网站
CuriosityStream is a streaming service with a tonne of interesting documentaries,
覆盖话题包括科学 自然 历史和科技
covering topics like: science, nature, history and technology.
CuriosityStream也有关于Stephen Hawking和David Attenborough的原创内容
CuriosityStream also has original content featuring the likes of Stephen Hawking and David Attenborough.
你可以点击下方链接 使用代码"primalspace"注册来免费观看
You can watch them all for free by visiting the link below and using the code "primalspace" to sign up.
可以获取一个月的试用 免费观看所有世界著名电影制作人的纪录片和纪实文学
This will give you a month of free access to every documentary and non-fiction title,
from some of the world's best filmmakers.
试用过后 续费只要每月2.99美元
After your first free month, you can continue your subscription for just $2.99 a month.
感谢观看 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video!